Meet Graciela Iturbide. She is one of
the most famous photographers from
Mexico. She captures cultures across
Mexico and the world along with their
everyday lives and rituals. Most of her
work is in black and white, vivid and
beautiful. These experiences become part
of her story and she becomes
part of theirs.
What cultures are part of your story?
One of her most famous photographs
is called Mujer ángel or Angel Woman. She looks like
she's about to take flight. The woman
lives traditionally in Mexico's remote
Sonora Desert,
yet she carries a boombox: evidence of
modern or more industrial culture
creeping in. Another famous photograph
shows a woman advertising her wares in
the local market,  in this case iguanas on
her head! Itubide eventually chose the
shot where the woman is strong and
determined. When you look at the contact
sheet, though, you'll see it took lots of
tries to get there. In some photos she
looks uncomfortable, like the iguanas are
going to spill off her head. But she's
also laughing, clearly enjoying her photo
shoot. In the 1980s Iturbide
photographed the “White Fence” area of
East LA.  Again, people seem to live in
between identities, both American and
Mexican. Another theme in Iturbide’s
work is birds. They can stand for ideas
about flight or escape because they're
not tethered to the earth. They can also
stand for a unique view-what Iturbide
refers to as “eyes that fly.” What do
the birds in your neighborhood see?
And then there are the cactus plants.
Iturbide finds beauty and stature in
the variety of cactus textures. Her
photography captures this and also plays
with the idea of the cactus as the most
representative plant of Mexico. When you
walk in your neighborhood,
what do you see?
Iturbide would want you to capture
your culture. She's waiting to see what
you come up with.
[Music]